Section 3.7 Combining strategies the
preceding sections have outlined
a wide array of strategies, each targeting
different facets
of AI risk. Synthesizing these into a
single coherent
plan is a difficult task. This section
outlines one
plausible strategic sequence illustrating
how different layers of defense
could be built upon one another to
navigate the
path from near term risks to long term
existential
challenges. This sequence is intended as
an illustrative model,
not as a definitive roadmap. Step 1
Foundational risk
management and Governance this is the
bedrock. Without a
safety culture and basic risk management,
technical solutions will
not be implemented correctly and labs will
race ahead
recklessly. The first common step is the
implementation of
robust risk management and governance
frameworks. While existing efforts
like the EU AI Act's Code of Practice
provide
a starting point, they have significant
limitations. For example,
capped fines, 7% of a company's annual
turnover may
not sufficiently deter well resourced
actors, and scope exemptions
for military or internal research leave
critical risk vectors
unaddressed. This highlights the necessity
for binding international governance.
Achieving such governance will likely
require building a broad
public and political consensus around the
importance of proactive
safety measures, making safety culture and
public outreach a
prerequisite for all other efforts. Step 2
Mitigating catastrophic
misuse we tackle misuse next because it is
a
present danger and the capabilities
required are sub AGI.
Success here, for example via access
controls and deep
acc, buys us time and builds the societal
muscles
for governing more powerful systems. The
second priority is
mitigating catastrophic misuse, a
challenge that is at least
conceptually more tractable than long term
alignment. The initial
line of defense is robust access control
for models
that exceed established risk thresholds,
preventing the trivial removal
of safeguards from open source models.
However, as dangerous
capabilities will inevitably proliferate.
This must be paired with
a proactive strategy of defense
acceleration to harden societal
infrastructure against attack.
Concurrently, socio technical strategies,
including clear
legislation, are crucial for preventing
the illicit use of
already proliferated AI. Step 3 Ensuring
control and alignment
of AGI as we approach AGI, we must assume
alignment is unsolved. Therefore, the
priority shifts to control
and monitoring transparent thoughts
evaluations. This is our safety
net. We scale capabilities only as fast as
we
can prove control. Managing the risks of
AGI misalignment
is, on paper harder than managing misuses.
A prudent
approach would be to prioritize
architectures that support transparent
thoughts, making systems more amenable to
monitoring and auditing,
while avoiding designs that encourage
opaque internal reasoning. These
systems must be subject to rigorous AI
control protocols
and evaluations. If audits reveal
alignment failures development must
be paused until they are rectified. This
paradigm of
carefully controlling potentially unsafe
systems must be paralleled by
an intensified research effort to solve
alignment with clear
red lines on capability scaling until
safety milestones are
met. Step 4 A robust solution for ASI
Alignment
finally, for the superhuman leap, direct
control is probably
impossible, but the strategy can become
meta. Use our
controlled AGI to automate alignment
research. This is our
best shot at a high reliability solution.
If this
fails, geopolitical strategies like
coordination or deterrence become the
last desperate lines of defense.
Developing a high reliability
solution for ASI alignment is the holy
grail. A
leading strategy is to leverage controlled
AGI to automate
alignment research. If successful, this
could lead to the
creation of inherently safe by design
systems. A powerful,
truly aligned ASI could then be used to
perform
a pivotal act that is a decisive
intervention designed
to permanently solve the global
coordination problem and end
the acute risk period from unaligned ASI
development. However,
if this research reveals that powerful AI
cannot be
created without unacceptable risks, the
international community would need
to coordinate a global pause or
moratorium. If such
world coordination proves impossible,
strategies of last resort, such
as deterrence regimes like MAIM might
become necessary to
prevent any single actor from unilaterally
developing uncontrollable ASI.
The textbook includes figure 3.29. Here it
depicts a
combined flowchart of safety strategies.
Of course, even this
fragile plan is the ideal plan. On paper,
it
might be the case that this plan is
insufficient
or completely different. For example, in
one scenario from
the AI 2027 forecast, humanity survives
not because of
a grand strategic plan, but despite the
failure of
most governance, coordination and
deterrence efforts. Instead, a scary
warning shot event galvanizes the leading
labs to slow
down and implement just enough technical
mitigations to avert
disaster. Mitigations that prove
insufficient in the scenario branches
where we lose control.